A Guide to the John Marshall Papers FA053
Rockefeller Archive Center
John Marshall papers
1925-1980, bulk 1940-1962
1940-1962
Rockefeller Archive Center
Marshall, John
Rockefeller Foundation
FA053
3.46 Cubic Feet 9 document cases
Biographical/Historical note
John Marshall (1903-1980) was born in Portland, Maine, completed undergraduate (1925) and graduate (1928) studies, and taught in the English department (1927-1933) at Harvard University. In 1933 he joined the Rockefeller Foundation as Assistant (later Associate) Director of the newly formed Humanities program, and from 1933 to 1940 served as a Director of Education with the General Education Board.
As an officer with the Rockefeller Foundation in a newly formed program, Mr. Marshall explored not only specific projects, but the concept of the humanities as a field. Mr. Marshall developed a concern in promoting world-wide culture, with a special interest in the Near East. The Rockefeller Foundation funding for the arts and humanities from 1933 to 1950 was approximately $4 million. Between 1951 and 1960, the support increased to $8.4 million, supporting projects in areas including language, radio, and motion pictures.
Mr. Marshall remained an Associate Director for the Humanities program when appointed as the first director for the newly acquired Villa Serbelloni in Bellagio, Italy, in 1959. The Villa was (and continues to be) used as a retreat for scholars in a variety of disciplines who were were working on intensive projects and as a conference center for international meetings focused on significant issues or scientific developments. As director, Marshall worked to develop the direction for the Villa, while maintaining his connections with the European humanities community.
John Marshall was married to Mary Gardner Marshall (1927-1960) and Charlotte Trowbridge Koechl Marshall (1961), and had two children from his first marriage, Mary Elizabeth Scott and Ann (Sister Mary John OSB). He was the author of "Classic Cooking" (1959).
Mr. Marshall retired from the Foundation in 1970 and died in 1980.
Scope and Contents note
The John Marshall Papers include correspondence, reports, speeches, articles, trip diaries, and photograph negatives. Materials span a period from his last semester at Harvard to condolences his widow received after his death. The bulk of the collection dates from 1940 to 1962.
The strength of the papers is that they reflect a more personal side to the humanities grant making of the Rockefeller Foundation. Mr. Marshall's personal correspondence differs greatly from that which was filed in the Rockefeller Foundation project files.
There is a great deal of material which documents the Rockefeller Foundation as a whole during the period, both in files pertaining to individuals, and in the files specifically identified as Rockefeller Foundation. There is extensive correspondence with individual grantees which does not appear in the official record of the Foundation, (Sisam, Flexner, St. John Perse) and correspondence commenting on specific grants by individuals who were not connected to them (Kirstein, Makinsky).
Arrangement note
The John Marshall Papers are divided into three series:
Series 1 - General Files
Series 2 - Villa Serbelloni Administration Files
Series 1062 - Photographs
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Related Archival Materials note
John Marshall was interviewed by the Columbia University Oral History Program in 1971. The transcript of the oral history interview, open with Mrs. Marshall's permission, is found in Record Group 13 of the Rockefeller Foundation Archives. Mr. Marshall's work at the Villa Serbelloni is documented in Record Group 3.2. His work as a director of the Humanities program of the Rockefeller Foundation is found in Record Group 3.1, and his diaries in Record Group 12 (almost seven cubic feet)document his work from 1933 to 1960.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 37
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of John Marshall come from two sources. The general files were given to the Rockefeller University by Charlotte Marshall (Mrs. John Marshall) in 1985. The Villa Serbelloni files were transferred from the Rockefeller Foundation.
Humanities
- General Files, 1925-1980, bulk 1940-1960; 1940-1960; 1; 1.2 Cubic Feet 3 document cases
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or topic.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes material relating directly to Rockefeller Foundation activities and to John Marshall's professional work.
  The files of speeches, articles, and thought pieces in Series 1 cover a range of topics and reflect Mr. Marshall's thoughts on the humanities program, 1933-1970. Most, but not all, were authorized by Mr. Marshall.
  Of special interest are the David H. Stevens file, which includes notes on his tenure at the Rockefeller Foundation and on Rockefeller Foundation Humanities personnel, 1929-1950, and the folder of General Education Board material, which deals with a review of interpretation at Colonial Williamsburg in 1939.
  - American Council of Learned Societies - "The Publication of Books by the ACLS - A Survey" by John Marshall, January 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Demographics, 1943, 1972, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnard, Chester, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Testimonials.
  - "Bulletin of the Rockefeller Foundation", January 1, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes history of the Humanities program and biographical notes on program officers; overview of work in all Rockefeller Foundation programs.
  - China Medical Board, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Darrell, Robert D., 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diaries - London, England, August 1, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Accounting of London listing various aspects of life, their condition and costs.
  - Diaries - Istanbul, Turkey, December 5-11, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Diaries - England, Near East, February 10-March 30, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    England, Beirut, Egypt, Baghdad, Syria, Istanbul, Ankara.
  - Diaries - Near East, February 18-April 6, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes summary reports on Egypt and Iraq.
  - Diaries - American West Coast, September 23-October 9, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Los Angeles, San Francisco, Portland, Seattle, Vancouver, Chicago, Louisville. Includes itinerary and program for 'Macbeth' in San Francisco on October 1. Diary only written through October 3.
  - Diaries - Near East, March 10-April 6, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Egypt, Lebanon, Baghdad, Istanbul, Ankara. Includes conversations and visits to past Rockefeller Foundation grantees as well as present and future ones. Talks with important artists, scholars and officials in the areas visited.
  - Diaries - Near East, March 6-21, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Philanthropy in Turkey.
  - Diaries - Europe, November 17-December 20, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    England, Netherlands, Switzerland, Paris.
  - Diaries - Europe and Near East, October 5-December 19, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes itinerary and local newspaper clippings.
  - Diaries - Italy, Paris, May 10-June 19, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flexner, James Thomas, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes proposal for book that became "An American Saga," which Flexner worked on while a resident at the Villa Serbelloni.
  - General Education Board - Colonial Williamsburg, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    "Some Educational Possibilities of the Restoration" by John Marshall, October 18, 1939, correspondence, 1934-1940.
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1953-1956, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Leger, Alexis (Saint-John Perse), 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    John Marshall campaigned with others for author to receive Nobel Prize (1960).
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Rockefeller Foundation Archives, Record Group 1.1, Series 200R, Box 241, Folders 2877-2878 (RF Refugee Scholar in French Literature).
  - Makinsky, Alexander, 1972-1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Marshall, Charlotte, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Marshall, John - Oral History, 1971-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Marshall, John - Personal, 1937-1944, 1969-1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Marshall, John - Poetry Book, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes draft of foreword, 'Petition' by W. H. Auden, with analysis by five readings.
  - Moe, Henry Allen, 1971-1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Office of War Information, January-June 1943 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    John Marshall was consultant; Anglo-American friction; Allan Nevins.
  - Olson, William C., 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Director of Villa Serbelloni immediately after John Marshall.
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1951, 1971-1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Archives, 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rockefeller Foundation/Nobel Symposia Villa Serbelloni Conference, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sawyer, Wilbur, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sisam, Kenneth, 1941-1948 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Much discussion of governments, politics, and life primarily from Sisam, although many copies of John Marshall letters also.
    See also Rockefeller Foundation Archives, Record Group 1.2, Series 401R files.
  - Speeches, Articles, and Thought Pieces - Miscellaneous, undated, 1944-1956 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Radio and motion pictures [their role in child development] notes for speech,undated; "Maalesh" excerpt by Jean Cocteau (in French), undated; Theater, undated (2); Travel, visit to post-war Europe outline, undated; University faculty, undated; "Public Opinion and The Emergency" memoranda from a [Rockefeller Foundation] group discussing the role of mass media after war was declared in Europe, November 1, 1939; Quotation from Paris Sous l'Occupation, by Jean-Paul Sartre, "La France Libre," November 15, 1944, Vol IX, no. 49; USSR/US/British diplomacy, September 23, 1946; "Spelman Messenger," August 1949, John Marshall gave the commencement address, June 6, 1949; also draft of speech topics include United Nations Education Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO), literature, importance of humanities; "The Vegetal Radicalism of Theodore Roethke", review in "The Sewanee Review", Winter 1950; "Radio's Uncertain Future" unpublished article, December 1950; Near East as viewed by American Education, 1951; Pugwash Conference on the Middle East, August 24, 1956.
  - Speeches, Articles, and Thought Pieces - Rockefeller Foundation, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Undated pieces: Criticism of the Humanities; Global war and the Rockefeller Foundation; Humanistic growth in the United States (2); Humanities audience; Humanities in Europe; Humanities and Foundations; Mass Communication; North American Regional Studies in the Rockefeller Foundation Humanities Program; Rockefeller Foundation in Post-war Great Britain; Widening Humanities; Working grammar for Foundation Officers in the arts.
  - Speeches, Articles, and Thought Pieces - Rockefeller Foundation (A - Humanities) (Box 3, Folder 36)
    "Adventuring in the Arts," The Rockefeller Foundation Confidential Monthly Report to the Trustees, written by Charles B. Fahs, and a special section on Music written by Marshall, April 1958; "Adventuring in the Arts" source material for the above and for a planned version on literature; Definition of a Foundation Officer, February 16, 1958; Exploring the American heritage, 1942, Article from the St. Paul "Dispatch"; Far Eastern Studies, February 19, 1946; History of the Rockefeller Foundation's program in the Humanities [1959]; Humanities [1953]; "Humanities Program and Related Foundation Interests in History 1950-1960."
  - Speeches, Articles, and Thought Pieces - Rockefeller Foundation (Humanists - North American) (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Humanists "Another Voice" February 19, 1945; International Library service "Books Across Frontiers" [1950]; Language program 1942; Library of Congress [1943]; Literature and Philanthropy October 1958; Near East trip 1950 talk to Rockefeller Foundation staff; North American studies May 5, 1942.
  - Speeches, Articles, and Thought Pieces - Rockefeller Foundation - Program (Box 3, Folder 38)
    "Program in the Humanities," The Rockefeller Foundation Confidential Monthly Report to the Trustees, February 1, 1951; "Relations of the Foundation with Governmental and Intergovernmental Agencies," 1950; Rockefeller Foundation in Post-war Europe, January 29, 1947; Rockefeller Foundation in underdeveloped countries (at the expense of established European and North American programs) 3 versions; "Supply of Minds," 1946; "The Symbol of History," Excerpt from Raymond B. Fosdick's Presidential Review 1944, includes total annual appropriations 1933-1944; "What to Do About the Humanities?" 1943 [?] article by George A. Lundberg about the position of the humanities in education with John Marshall's response (unpublished) and correspondence.
  - Stevens, David H., 1949, 1972-1980 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Includes biographical sketches of Rockefeller Foundation Humanities personnel.
  - United Nations Education Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO), 1948 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Weaver, Warren, 1940, 1951-1978 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Includes Warren Weaver articles, correspondence, Lewis Carroll/"Alice in Wonderland".
  - Whiting, Bartlett Jere, 1925, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Christmas Greetings to John Marshall from the Philharmonia Hungarica (oversize material), 1957 (Box 7, Folder 88)
- Villa Serbelloni Administrative Files, 1959-1967, bulk 1959-1961; 1959-1961; 2; 1.2 Cubic Feet 3 document cases
  The series documents the beginnings of the Villa Serbelloni program from John Marshall's first days at the Villa. The bulk of the series dates prior to 1963, at which time correspondence and filing procedures were established and all documents concerning the Villa went directly through the Rockefeller Foundation's records management program. These documents are found in Record Group 3.2 of the Rockefeller Foundation Archives.
  Especially interesting are the diaries for 1960 when it was not clear what the Villa program was going to be and Mr. Marshall traveled through Europe looking for possibilities. Included in this series is a copy of John Marshall's unpublished history of the Villa.
  Mr. Marshall's file titles have been largely unchanged in this series.
  Rockefeller Foundation Archives, Record Group 3.2, Series 900, files on Villa Serbelloni.
  - American Studies in Europe, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Anderle, Othman - Institute for Theoretische Geschichte, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Architecture and City Planning (Milan), 1960 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Austria, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Barraclough, Geoffrey - World History, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Bonnefoy, Yves, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Butterfield, Herbert - Historiography, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - "The Castle's Keep: The Villa Serbelloni in History" (Box 4, Folder 50)
    John Marshall's unpublished history 1970 corrected copy with footnotes.
  - "The Castle's Keep: The Villa Serbelloni in History" (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - "The Castle's Keep: The Villa Serbelloni in History" (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    Potential publication of the Villa history.
  - Ceccato, Silvio - Language, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Centre Internationale de Prospective, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Diary, August 1959 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    John Marshall's first days at the Villa.
  - Ernst, Fritz, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Evans, Ifor - English Language, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Eyuboglu, Bedri Rahmie, 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    Scope and Contents
    The correspondence includes original artwork in a variety of mediums.
  - Fondation Europeenne de la Culture, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Hersch, Jeanne (Goormaghtigh, John), 1960 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - History Education in Europe, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - History of the Resistance Movement in Europe, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Humanities - New York Office - Correspondence, 1959-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Humanities - New York Office - Correspondence, 1959-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Humanities - New York Office - Correspondence, 1959-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Humanities - New York Office - Correspondence, 1959-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Humanities - New York Office - Correspondence, 1959-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Humanities - Villa Serbelloni (A-Z), 1959-1963 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    Correspondence, interviews, reports on specific or potential Humanities projects in Europe.
  - Humanities - Villa Serbelloni (A-Z), 1959-1963 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Instituto Italiano di Studi Storici, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Italy, 1946-April 1, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    Rockefeller Foundation appropriations to Italy.
  - Opera Performances on Television, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Pellegrini, Alessandro, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Rossi, Paolo, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Rossi, Pietro, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Rossi-Landi, Ferruccio, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Switzerland, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Travel - Frankfurt, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Travel - Munich, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Travel - Hamburg, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Travel - German Diaries, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Travel - Turkey, 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Vaughan, Denis, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Wine Stock, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Yalman, Ahmed Emin, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Proficiency Diploma in Italian to John Marshall, 1960; Large format. (Box 7, Folder 87)
- John Marshall photographs, 1062
  Biographical / Historical
  John Marshall (1903-1980) was born in Portland, Maine, completed undergraduate (1925) and graduate (1928) studies, and taught in the English department (1927-1933) at Harvard University. In 1933 he joined the Rockefeller Foundation as Assistant (later Associate) Director of the newly formed Humanities program, and from 1933 to 1940 served as a Director of Education with the General Education Board.
  As an officer with the Rockefeller Foundation in a newly formed program, Mr. Marshall explored not only specific projects, but the concept of the humanities as a field. Mr. Marshall developed a concern in promoting world-wide culture, with a special interest in the Near East. The Rockefeller Foundation funding for the arts and humanities from 1933 to 1950 was approximately $4 million. Between 1951 and 1960, the support increased to $8.4 million, supporting projects in areas including language, radio, and motion pictures.
  Mr. Marshall remained an Associate Director for the Humanities program when appointed as the first director for the newly acquired Villa Serbelloni in Bellagio, Italy, in 1959. The Villa was (and continues to be) used as a retreat for scholars in a variety of disciplines who were were working on intensive projects and as a conference center for international meetings focused on significant issues or scientific developments. As director, Marshall worked to develop the direction for the Villa, while maintaining his connections with the European humanities community.
  John Marshall was married to Mary Gardner Marshall (1927-1960) and Charlotte Trowbridge Koechl Marshall (1961), and had two children from his first marriage, Mary Elizabeth Scott and Ann (Sister Mary John OSB). He was the author of "Classic Cooking" (1959).
  Mr. Marshall retired from the Foundation in 1970 and died in 1980.
  Photographs
  - John Marshall - Luce Turnier (Box 55, Folder 681)
  - John Marshall - Miscellaneous (Box 56, Folder 682)